[SPEAKER_05]: So, this is the Chula Vedala Sutta, and I've shortened it a bit, just to make it con... yeah, make it concise.
[SPEAKER_05]: There are many questions in it, and they are asked by a layman called Visakha, and he asks a nun, Damodina.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the first question he asks is, in what sense does the Buddha refer to the term Sakaya?
[SPEAKER_05]: Sakaya, sakaya.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_05]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_05]: And the translation for that is... well, there's many different types, but it's identity, identity view, personality view, or embodiment.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it's person, identified, body.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what... in what sense does the Buddha refer to sakaya?
[SPEAKER_05]: And the answer to that is the five assumed aggregates are referred to as sakāya.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is form, feeling, perception, saṅkharas and consciousness.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what sense does the Buddha use the term sakāya?
[SPEAKER_05]: What would your translation be for that?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Personality... Because that is the five assumed aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's any notion of personality, any notion of identification with anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why, as far as the extent of identification goes, as far as the extent of Sakaya goes, it's to the extent of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: You cannot be identified with anything else that's not within five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, it's interesting to see that the person asking this is not asking what is myself.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the Self?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is atta?
[SPEAKER_05]: Atta, what is that?
[SPEAKER_05]: He's asking what is Sakaya?
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, means he already kind of understood the difference there.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is this person?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's that ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, you can't have... you can't have attavāda, you can't have the Self of you without underlying ownership, but you can still have the underlying ownership without a Self of you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, unquestioned ownership of your five aggregates is how and why the Atavāda exists for people.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is why they think in terms of I was in the past, I will be in the future and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, when you start uprooting that, it's not going to happen overnight and it's not just like a flipping a switch and now everything is suddenly not self and not mayātā and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: The coarser symptoms of that ownership that you have in regard to the aggregates, the coarser symptoms would
[SPEAKER_03]: You fall off.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, you're still gonna have subtler levels of identification and ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: With what?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, with form, or with feeling, or with perception, or with activities, or with consciousness.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can't be something other than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: For him, he's already... Well, he already, yeah, he already has had some understanding.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that question that he asked already implies knowledge to a degree of distinguishing between, oh, what is my self?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because see, if he approached and said, okay, that atta and that anatta that the Lord teaches, what is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Then she says, oh, it's the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would not be an accurate answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: That would be quite a misleading answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that is not what atta is.
[SPEAKER_03]: Atta is the result of that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it's that ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's what he was referring to when he asked about sakāyā.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, can you find any sense of ownership apart, outside, away from this body, this experience as a whole?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why it kind of implies that embodiment of ownership, it's bound with this, with this form, with this what you are.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, to what extent?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's to the extent you've been maintaining the ownership carelessly, but unless a person is an arahant, there's always going to be some degree of it present.
[SPEAKER_03]: That conceit, identification and ownership.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also interesting that thus corresponds five, I assume, aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's also the summary of the First Noble Truth of Dukkha.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the exact same, not anything different.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, right, right.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, well, it's... it's the same inside, really.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just explained in...
[SPEAKER_03]: In different ways, different terms.
[SPEAKER_03]: Described differently, but it's the same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because the... the root... the ownership is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: The identification is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: The craving is the root of suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when there is craving, there is ownership.
[SPEAKER_02]: And there's ownership as craving.
[SPEAKER_02]: But the identification is not explicit, like, I am this, or I am that feeling, or I am this body, or I am...
[SPEAKER_02]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's not.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's more... That's already like...
[SPEAKER_03]: Implied in your... how you act, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, how you perceive.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's also...
[SPEAKER_03]: It presupposes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, any perception you have, it presupposes already ownership.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's already there, as an underlying basis.
[SPEAKER_03]: So...
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not on the level of choice whereby I choose to not identify.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, this aggregate is impermanent and this is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_03]: You're doing that with your ownership already.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's non-specific.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, the only way to kind of remove the ownership is to start undermining it indirectly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because whatever you directly take to tell yourself that it's not yours, well, that experience as a whole is yours.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then you... that's what we said, like with... with atta, he would be perceiving an atta.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, this is not self, this is not that.
[SPEAKER_03]: But perceiving the not-self is done with your sense of self.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not... it's not just so easily... you can't so easily wiggle out of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the second question is, what is the source of sakāya, that identity?
[SPEAKER_05]: And you basically answer that.
[SPEAKER_05]: It is the craving for the perpetuation of being, or existence, and delighting and lusting here and there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what keeps your ownership perpetuated, which is what then simultaneously feeds this gratuitous assumption of I am, and who I am, and what I am, and to what extent I am, and what is mine, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a symptom.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is the ending of sakāyā?
[SPEAKER_03]: Removal of the craving, desire, restraining desire and lust, till the craving is understood, abandoned, dispassion, experienced, there is no more ownership, then thus sakāyā cannot possibly persist.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, the complete dispassion, abandoning, rejection, freedom and attachment from craving.
[SPEAKER_04]: But that's an indirect process in terms of allowing craving
[SPEAKER_04]: To arise without acting out of it is... you're not trying to get rid of the craving, in terms of not allowing it to arise.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's a kind of a topic in itself.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's unavoidable.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to get rid of the craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to abandon the craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what does that getting rid of mean and abandoning?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, we covered that in other talks.
[SPEAKER_03]: It does not mean denying it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It does not mean, get rid of this, get rid of this, because that's just another thing you're doing out of your craving now, against that.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you're full of aversion towards it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Satisfying it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Certainly not.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, basically, whether you're satisfying it, or you're trying to deny it, or you're ignoring it, all of those would be acting out of that craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's exactly why the practice of dhamma is subtle, and it's not just a question of countering.
[SPEAKER_03]: When this arises with that arises, it's about discerning the middle way in between.
[SPEAKER_03]: But,
[SPEAKER_03]: As far as the answer to the question goes, yes, by abandonment or craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, the next question can be asked, what, how do I abandon that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, then you go to every talk we did on the gradual training, the entirety of it, that's how you abandon it.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, so that is, yeah, how, and it's the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's how you... Oh, well, there you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe just read the sutra then.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, exactly, because there is exactly that tendency of, alright, same with you, like, okay, so this is not myself now, so I'm dealing with it, or, okay, so I'm not craving now, I shall abandon this craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, craving, get rid of the craving, I must not crave, I must not crave.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, that's all just wishful thinking now, and you're trying to jump at the end, at the result of what, yes, you need to abandon it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same when we spoke about those hindrances before, when people can't come to terms with learning how to be
[SPEAKER_03]: You're not being patient in regard to them, but feeling fully justified in being averse towards the mind of, you know, experiencing pleasure or pain and just trying to get rid of it, just trying to counter it and antidote it with a method, with a technique, with... and feeling justified in doing so.
[SPEAKER_03]: As a... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: You have to be able to see that mind for what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you have to recognize that, well, you are already within the craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you can't just...
[SPEAKER_03]: I got to get rid of this craving without that being also part of that craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, how do I deal with this?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a valid question.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you deal with this by not trying to get rid of it, by not thinking it's on the level of choice or antidoting your unpleasant experiences that you are fundamentally still averse to.
[SPEAKER_03]: But by recognizing, right, that's the gradual training, the Noble Eightfold Path, the entirety, starting from the livelihood, speech, bodily actions, precepts, sense restraint, all of that is your way out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not like something you do on a side, you know, sometimes, but then I relax on the weekends, but then I'm back onto it on Monday.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Your whole existence is being reshaped by that
[SPEAKER_03]: Entirety of the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why, when the Buddha did describe what's the way out, that's the way out.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is nothing shorter than that, that can be the way out.
[SPEAKER_03]: If it were, it's not the way out.
[SPEAKER_02]: What comes up often is, I want something palpable to do.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, how to deal with that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's too ambitious for me.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's a lot of palpable stuff.
[SPEAKER_03]: Such as keeping the precepts?
[SPEAKER_03]: That's very palpable.
[SPEAKER_03]: When you want to look at things that are rooted in greed, aversion, delusion, you don't.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's something you can do as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Keep your mouth shut when you want to say something.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's something you can do.
[SPEAKER_03]: Don't go out into the crowd or company.
[SPEAKER_03]: Stay alone in the group.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's something you can do.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, but it's not what I want to do.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, give me something palpable to do that I also want to do and that will result in the immediate pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's not the practice of the dhamma then.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, depending how you look at it, there are lots of palpable things to do, and more than enough, actually.
[SPEAKER_05]: Give me something quick.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, well, that's really what's being asked.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, but come on, just give me something that would take me all the way there, without all of this.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, to find something I can hammer away at.
[SPEAKER_05]: Just straightforward.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just give me a view that I can agree with, that will make me feel like I'm absolved from responsibility and duty, and thus I'll be saved.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just, that's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, is the assumption of the upādāna, in terms of the five aggregates, is the assumption of ownership the exact same thing as the five assumed aggregates, or is this assumption one thing and the five assumed aggregates another?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, is my identity separate from those aggregates, or is it the same?
[SPEAKER_04]: The five aggregates don't depend on craving at all, or clinging at all, but clinging depends on the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: So, it's like a parasite, almost, in... What is a parasite?
[SPEAKER_04]: The assumption.
[SPEAKER_04]: Upādāna.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, upādāna is not the form, feeling, perception, saṅkhara's consciousness.
[SPEAKER_02]: I mean, it depends on...
[SPEAKER_02]: But it depends on them.
[SPEAKER_04]: No, the the five aggregates
[SPEAKER_04]: Don't depend on the upādāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, but that's not the question.
[SPEAKER_03]: The question is, is upādāna different from the five aggregates or not?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, it's not separate from the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's not separate?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if it's not separate, does it mean it's one of them?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the same as them?
[SPEAKER_04]: The way I understand it is, it's like...
[SPEAKER_04]: Well, you used the word, like, bridging, in terms of, it's, yeah, it's like, rests on top of the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, it's a different thing than five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's neither.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, as in, it's, I was thinking like a simile would be kind of like rust, as in, it's not, the rust is not a separate thing from the metal, but it's not, it is not the metal in itself, it is kind of part of the
[SPEAKER_00]: It's, it's, it's not, it's not, it's neither the five aggregates, nor is it a separate thing, the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: Right, but can we come up with a better example then, with a more accurate example?
[SPEAKER_03]: I see what you're saying, but you could peel off the rust and you've got a separate thing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: You've got a separate thing, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So what cannot be peeled off, the five aggregates, but it's not the five aggregates, but it cannot be found apart from them?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, upādāna is that, but can we find a simile for it?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, something that's not the thing, but it cannot exist without the thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: The reason I'm asking for simile means, if you can come up with a simile, you're understanding the principle.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not asking for a specific simile.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm asking for anything that would represent it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like a parasite?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, parasite, you know, exists on its own, then it comes and feeds on you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you could separate it from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You see, yeah, Gagan, you can kind of separate it, but not quite.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like cancer was another example I thought of, that it is not... it can't exist on its own, apart from the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not the body, but it kind of... Can we have it with a different sound?
[SPEAKER_00]: Another one.
[SPEAKER_03]: Something else.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's too ready for me, isn't it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Something more accurate.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'll add one strike.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it cannot be found from the five aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: It cannot be found apart from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's not it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, is this the thing?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, but I want an example.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't want...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not asking for an answer to what I just gave the answer to.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the example?
[SPEAKER_03]: Like any example of something that is generated by something else, and to that extent it exists.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if that thing stops generating it, it cannot exist anymore.
[SPEAKER_03]: It cannot exist on its own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like a fire burning a fuel.
[SPEAKER_03]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Candle, light, flame, anything generated by a burning candle, wick, fat, oxygen.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's not it.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, there is a heat in regard to a candle or light, you could say, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you just take that apart from the candle?
[SPEAKER_03]: It's inconceivable.
[SPEAKER_03]: It cannot exist anywhere apart from that source of fire.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's not it.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you touch the flame, if you look at it, you won't find the heat in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You won't find the light in it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And, yeah, and that's also how, I think, other suttas as well talk about upādāna, taking up a fuel, burning.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, the aggregates are the fuel.
[SPEAKER_02]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, depends.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, practically speaking, I don't think you need to now differentiate the layers of fuel, but you need to recognize that the assumption, the identity, the ownership won't be measurable by what you can observe, because what you can observe is the level of the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you could say aggregates are the fuel, but not on their own.
[SPEAKER_03]: What... what is it that makes the aggregates fuel?
[SPEAKER_03]: What lights them up?
[SPEAKER_02]: Lust.
[SPEAKER_02]: Lust, yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Desire and lust in regard to the observable, in regard to the attended, in regard to the direct experience.
[SPEAKER_03]: Desire and lust.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why there is a heat of ātmādeya.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why there is a sense of self-enduring.
[SPEAKER_03]: That then you end up assuming, because see, like, all this light here, it's separate from...
[SPEAKER_03]: I see the candle because of the light.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, the light comes first.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so when one is approaching the dhamma, one already finds the fire burning.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, whether one approaches or not, one is already thoroughly burning.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, so there's no neutral position.
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: There's already fuel and it's already on fire.
[SPEAKER_03]: So you need to see, like, if you...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so now, this light revealed here, reveals a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: What do I do with it?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do I deal with it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, you have to find the source of the fire.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can be trying to, you know, dim the light and get rid of, dissipate the heat and manage all the all the secondary, but for as long as the main source is still being fueled and burning, well, the fire will carry on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's exactly when the Buddha would say, like, well, a person reflecting wisely on his own situation
[SPEAKER_03]: He will not dwell and invest effort into questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, so was I in the past?
[SPEAKER_03]: Will I be in the future?
[SPEAKER_03]: What am I now?
[SPEAKER_03]: How did it end?
[SPEAKER_03]: Trying to satisfy the already proliferated craving upon craving upon craving for answers and who I am and what I am and seeking safety on that level.
[SPEAKER_03]: He would recognize, okay, like the Buddha says, the problem is desire and passion.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, I have all this pressuring answer I need to clarify, but let me do things in the order he said you should do them.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, first keep the precepts, guard the sense doors, dwell restrained, and then you'll see that probably 80% of your questions will subside, because they got dissolved now.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no more fire fueling the pressure of finding these random answers.
[SPEAKER_03]: You realize, ah, that was all rooted in me just not wanting to deal with the fire.
[SPEAKER_03]: That was unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Once I became aware of it.
[SPEAKER_02]: So, you have to recognize what the fuel is and stop.
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you stop it?
[SPEAKER_02]: How do you stop it?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you stop
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: But what if you don't see the specific connections?
[SPEAKER_03]: Would you then stop keeping the precepts?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why not?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because basic... because the precepts... because
[SPEAKER_02]: Not keeping the precepts is affirming the wrong view, basically.
[SPEAKER_02]: It's affirming that the problem is not in the fuel, but in me being burnt.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you already know where the problem is, basically, by keeping the precepts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you don't need to keep the precepts to then find out, later on, these connections and stuff that will then justify.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, you already know.
[SPEAKER_03]: You already have a... and everybody does, to some extent.
[SPEAKER_03]: They just don't know the extent of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But everybody can already recognize that, yeah, I can already...
[SPEAKER_03]: If somebody just comes out of blue and says, okay, well, here are two options.
[SPEAKER_03]: One fuels the fire, one diminishes it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which one would it be?
[SPEAKER_03]: And then the option, the A, B, C, would be sensuality, restraint, ill-will, non-ill-will, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Even the most uneducated person, if it's honest, will already... 99% of them will get the right answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: You already have a very good inkling what increases the burning and what decreases it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just staying, committing to it, dealing with it to the extent necessary, enduring it, not going back and forgetting the bigger picture.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's where people need encouragement and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Knowing what to emphasize.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, if I emphasize to you, no, no, no, it's when this mind moment of craving happens, well, in between that space you stop and that's it, that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, okay, now I'll get these abstract ideas that I would confuse for practical instruction.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everything else becomes second, because I emphasize these results of the successful practice that I don't really partake in, because I haven't fulfilled the gradual training.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's when people say...
[SPEAKER_03]: The Buddha talked about the properties of nibbāna, pretty much being universal, what nibbāna is, yeah?
[SPEAKER_03]: So then it's like, okay, so then that applies to me as well.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, yeah, the five aggregates, they cannot be appropriated.
[SPEAKER_03]: Upādāna is not the aggregates.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is the element of nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, I'm already in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to do anything.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, that's not an uncommon view.
[SPEAKER_03]: The entire Buddhist schools evolved from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, you're already in nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just stop forgetting it, type of thing.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's like you're not.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, in every ill person,
[SPEAKER_03]: There is an element of health, i.e.
[SPEAKER_03]: there is a possibility of cure.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that doesn't mean that while he's still sick, he's cured, because he could be cured.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, it's sticking to it, to the cure, to the prescribed cure, which is the Noble Eightfold Path.
[SPEAKER_03]: That again, as I said, if you're honest, you realize you don't need much convincing.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you're honest, you realize, yeah, you've got a sense restraint, of course,
[SPEAKER_03]: I can't be acting out of these things and at the same time expecting mine to go beyond it all, when the slightest desire or ill will or irritation or laziness just makes you act and commit to it and want to not deal with anything else.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why the Buddha referred... or one of the main... was it the main factor that he praised that would, like, be a common thread from somebody who's a bhutujjana to an arahant would be diligence.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not perceiving the light and floating in the air or having jhanic ecstatic experiences or whatever else.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Diligence.
[SPEAKER_03]: Diligently not abandoning what you know you should be doing.
[SPEAKER_03]: There you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Nothing mystical about it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Which is exactly why it's not very popular.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yes, the desire and lust for the five assumed aggregates is the assumption there.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why the assumption is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what fuels it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how does sakāya come about?
[SPEAKER_05]: How does identity come about?
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's when an uninstructed ordinary person has not seen the noble ones.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, he doesn't know what to emphasize, really.
[SPEAKER_05]: He just, yeah, identified with everything.
[SPEAKER_05]: And how does identity view, sakāya, not come about?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's when an instructed noble disciple has seen the noble ones, heard their teachings, skilled and trained in their teachings, they don't regard form as self.
[SPEAKER_05]: Self as having form.
[SPEAKER_05]: They don't regard feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how do you not regard the five aggregates?
[SPEAKER_05]: As yours.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: How do you do that?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how did that noble disciple, who has met
[SPEAKER_03]: The wise ones... How did he arrive to the point of not regarding these things?
[SPEAKER_03]: Did he just started not regarding things because he was told the esoteric truth that uninitiated were not privy to?
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how did he do it?
[SPEAKER_04]: By not acting out of...
[SPEAKER_04]: Craving this assumption of... How do you start that?
[SPEAKER_04]: How do you begin that practice?
[SPEAKER_04]: Virtue, sense of strength.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by hearing what he needs to do first and actually doing it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the great mystery.
[SPEAKER_00]: Intelligence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, he went and visited other teachers who said, well, nobody gets killed.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's nothing given.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's nothing lost.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no life.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no death.
[SPEAKER_03]: There are no brahmas.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's just what you have.
[SPEAKER_03]: He's just telling, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, he went to another teacher, and he told him something on the same level, or another teacher taught him how to watch sensations, and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, they came to the noble one, and he told him, well, keep the precepts, guard the sense doors, don't go after things that are inducive of lust, don't act out of aversion, don't act out of carelessness, don't act out of hindrances.
[SPEAKER_03]: Endure that.
[SPEAKER_03]: The confinement that builds up,
[SPEAKER_03]: Again, you have to get used to it, stop resisting it, stop being averse towards that, dwell in solitude, watch your intentions, and everything else then will fall into place.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, the form will not be regarded as yours, the feeling will not be regarded as yours, even if you wanted to, because you thoroughly endured the unknown ability of it, which is the... was the scary or unpleasant part.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by being instructed rightly, he applied the effort of sense-restraint, guarding of the sense-doors, enduring the confinement, not acting out of hindrances, not trying to get rid of them and so on, and now he's skilled in not regarding form as his.
[SPEAKER_03]: But he was not just, oh, this is how you do it, okay, thank you, and everything else we just sweep under the carpet and you just come straight to the application of the result of your supposed application.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nothing is real.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, or just dismissing it and so on.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, is the Noble Eightfold Path conditioned or unconditioned?
[SPEAKER_05]: It's conditioned.
[SPEAKER_05]: You don't just... What's the Noble Eightfold Path, da-da-da?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, okay.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I got it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I got it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I understood that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I listed it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I studied the etymology of every term.
[SPEAKER_03]: All the permutations, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I memorized it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Four different ikāyas, and that's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I understand the Noble Eightfold Path now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Does that make it understood?
[SPEAKER_03]: No?
[SPEAKER_04]: Conditioned by what?
[SPEAKER_04]: This clarity of, firstly, not contradicting what is being said, yeah, keeping the precepts, yeah, acting virtuously.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's the first condition.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And... Acting rightly, abstaining from wrong acts, by body, by speech.
[SPEAKER_04]: Then, through that, it's possible to see the danger of acting out of craving.
[SPEAKER_03]: But see, what will... What also?
[SPEAKER_03]: See, if you're not acting out of desire, ill-will, hindrances, if you have heard the dhamma, you're not acting out of these things, what else is being developed there?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well... What are you developing by not acting?
[SPEAKER_03]: The strengthening of the mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_04]: Perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: What is the strengthening of the mind?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's composure.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by not acting out, you are developing the samādhi.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that there would be another condition, so to speak, of the path.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sīla, samādhi, pañña.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Eightfold path.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, by not getting composure...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, by not acting out, by having the mental strength to not try to get rid of things as soon as they arise,
[SPEAKER_03]: You are establishing perspective now.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like, wait, but I don't...
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't need to get rid of this.
[SPEAKER_03]: That was not the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that will never occur to you, if you were too busy trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_05]: And perspective is that wisdom.
[SPEAKER_05]: And that's the perspective, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when that perspective is just unshakable, whichever way you turn it, the perspective remains correctly established and, yeah, there's not much to do anymore.
[SPEAKER_04]: The mind is easier and easier to tame.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, of course.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same like with any other wild animal.
[SPEAKER_03]: The beginning is the hardest.
[SPEAKER_05]: It says, are the three categories, sīla, samādhi, pañña, virtue, composure, perspective and wisdom, included in the Noble Eightfold Path?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is the Noble Eightfold Path included in the three categories?
[SPEAKER_04]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_04]: Noble Eightfold Path is included in the three categories.
[SPEAKER_04]: What does that mean?
[SPEAKER_04]: It can be summarized in the way that we just described.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so the three categories are the more fundamental three aspects, that then you can further define into eightfold path.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's really the three layers of development, which we said, yeah, precepts of virtue,
[SPEAKER_03]: So, these three categories, are they linear or non-linear?
[SPEAKER_05]: Non-linear.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_05]: So... You don't, you don't do one and then...
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's not like... Like on the other one.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, by knowing the three categories, by knowing that the category of sīla, so to speak, well, see, there you go.
[SPEAKER_03]: Means the category of some perspective has to be there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, you wouldn't stick to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You wouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Means a degree of composure has to be there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Otherwise, again, you would just be pulled left and right by any idea you have.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, they come together.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you will... You can then emphasize one, but by doing so, the other two are being developed through.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not, I do one, then I move on to the next one and forget about the first one.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Developing one, you're developing the two.
[SPEAKER_03]: Developing the two, you're developing the third one.
[SPEAKER_03]: Doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is composure?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is samādhi?
[SPEAKER_05]: What things are foundations of samādhi?
[SPEAKER_05]: What things are the prerequisites of samādhi?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the development of samādhi?
[SPEAKER_05]: You just answer that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That elevation of mind is samādhi.
[SPEAKER_05]: The four bases of present mindfulness.
[SPEAKER_00]: Four foundations.
[SPEAKER_05]: Four foundations of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_05]: The four right efforts are prerequisites for samādhi.
[SPEAKER_05]: The cultivation, development, and making much of these very same things is development of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's four right efforts, foundations of mindfulness, and any elevation of mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Composure.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Imperceptibility, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, then you go, how many saṅkhara are there?
[SPEAKER_05]: There are three.
[SPEAKER_05]: There are these three saṅkharas.
[SPEAKER_05]: Physical or bodily, verbal and mental.
[SPEAKER_05]: Kāyā-saṅkhara, vaci-saṅkhara, citta-saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the bodily determination, the kāyā-saṅkhara?
[SPEAKER_05]: What determines the body?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, it doesn't determine the body.
[SPEAKER_05]: What activates the body?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the bodily activity?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the bodily activity?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, I mean, the answer is the breath.
[SPEAKER_04]: But you could also, like, say, the heart or the functioning brain.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't understand.
[SPEAKER_03]: Activity.
[SPEAKER_03]: Activity requires an intention.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, because it's choice.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: There is a degree of intentionality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's like the closest neutral, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It is, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that's why the breathing is inseparable from the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Cannot be conceived apart from the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's a bodily activity.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, yeah, it does still imply a certain degree of intention.
[SPEAKER_02]: Intentionality.
[SPEAKER_03]: Unlike operation of other organs.
[SPEAKER_02]: And what about being in a body posture?
[SPEAKER_02]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well... That depends on all that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's kind of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Practically, obviously, you could practice on the level of bodily postures, but it's not... it's not necessarily always revealing the activity aspect.
[SPEAKER_03]: And breathing is.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, body posture is more like on the level of, yeah,
[SPEAKER_03]: Recognizing there is a beating heart, that you don't really have that...
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't require that direct say or direct input.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just find yourself seated or standing and so on.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, you had the intention to change,
[SPEAKER_03]: But now, you are seated.
[SPEAKER_03]: Breath is always engaging.
[SPEAKER_03]: Breath is always active, in that sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: What were you going to say, sorry?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it just occurred to me, in relation to your question.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you can do a heart transplant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you can take somebody's heart out, put it in a box, and it sort of keeps beating.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you cannot take the breath out in the same way.
[SPEAKER_02]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so that's why in-and-out breathing is the bodily activity of the fundamental kind.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is the verbal vācī-saṅkāra, the verbal activator?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is that?
[SPEAKER_04]: Thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is that, specifically, when it comes to speaking?
[SPEAKER_02]: It's, eh... first one, the things, and then the practice of speaking.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's how it happens.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is that thinking?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the extent of that thinking and pondering?
[SPEAKER_03]: I guess that's what I'm asking.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the extent of the vācchasankhāra?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the extent of the intentional activity?
[SPEAKER_02]: Because there's the sankhāra aspect of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, the assumption to externalize that thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Externalize, between quotes, that's sort of the problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, is that assumption, that assumption to externalize, to use that description, is that another thought?
[SPEAKER_04]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I would say it's actually more fundamental than that.
[SPEAKER_03]: How can... what would that be then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, yeah, I'm not saying that it's not also a thought, but it's like, you can have all sorts of particular thoughts about this, that and the other, but then, as a determination for speech, there would be something which is a bit... which is still a thought, but it seems to be more deeply rooted.
[SPEAKER_05]: It assumes...
[SPEAKER_03]: Deeply rooted into what?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, in relation to perhaps more particular thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's another thought, then?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not denying that it is also another thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: But what else is, if it's not just a thought?
[SPEAKER_03]: Because you keep saying it's not...
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm not denying it's also not a thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: What else is it, beside the thought?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can it be something else?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe what I try to say is that... that it's... that it's held more deeply than sort of...
[SPEAKER_03]: Deep to what?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the surface that you measure the depth from?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, let me put it the other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: Are you saying it's exactly on the same level as every other thought?
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't want to give you the answer before you answer me.
[SPEAKER_03]: We'll arrive at it, but it is quite useful where you...
[SPEAKER_02]: It's quite useful where you started.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's exactly why people don't understand the extent of thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because they keep thinking there's something more to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that more, it's only more because you assumed it to be outside of your thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: And exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Deeper.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you start looking at the depth, you realize, well, it can only be a thought.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, for as long as I don't open my mouth and utter,
[SPEAKER_03]: Voice, air, sounds...
[SPEAKER_03]: I am not speaking.
[SPEAKER_03]: It doesn't matter how much deeply I go into verbal thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you want to stop the vāci-sankhāra?
[SPEAKER_03]: Stop speaking, and stop assuming the speech through your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't have to shut your thoughts, or even verbal speaking, you don't have to shut down, in order to be quiet.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's not what a speech is.
[SPEAKER_03]: It says, like, the vāci-sankhāra, the activity of breaking into speech, the necessary activity for it, is thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: On that verbal kind.
[SPEAKER_03]: But you realize, for as long as you're not breaking into speech, it's gonna be thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Doesn't matter how you feel in regard to it, and what assumptions float around, and if your mouth is all pressured to say something,
[SPEAKER_03]: Breaking into speech happens in its own domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: And this does not enter that domain.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, what determines the breaking into speech, if it's not that thinking and pondering?
[SPEAKER_03]: The domain of verbal possibility of speaking.
[SPEAKER_03]: The domain of having a mouth that can utter voices.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, but whether it does or not, still involves some sort of intention there.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's my point.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no transition of that intention.
[SPEAKER_03]: It involves intention to think and ponder and say something, which is not on the level of speech.
[SPEAKER_03]: When it is, it's because it came on from its own domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: The speech comes from its own domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because thinking and pondering to speak is in its own domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no overlap.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no one goes into the other and then your voice comes out.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the self-centered point of view.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you understand the extent of vittaka vichara correctly...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's almost understanding the limit correctly.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's what extent means, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: And not assume that there is...
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, this is the limit and then my speech is outside, which is another vittāka-vicāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you realize, well, how do then I access the domain of speech?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, by speaking.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can't access it with your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_03]: In the same sense, your mind does not sit in your body, does not access your form.
[SPEAKER_03]: It just overlaps through assumption and assumes it's in it and vice versa.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's that converging point of speech, of verbal saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_03]: Mouth is physical, sounds are physical, it's own level of the form, but it's your thinking and pondering that does not know its own extent, that you assume.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, I have said this, and it went out.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: I'm thinking of saying it, and then the body is speaking for me.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's pretty much what I'm saying.
[SPEAKER_03]: But now you can accept that as information, sure, but you really need to see it on the level of your acute thinking and pondering as a verbal saṅkhāra.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a verbal saṅkhāra means that thinking and pondering determines the possibility... Means talking to yourself in your own mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Ah, yes.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what it means practically.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's a verbal saṅkhāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's not speech.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not speech.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: It determines speech, but it's like... Well, see, why does it determine speech?
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's... let me stop answering it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me start asking questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why does speaking to yourself, in your own mind, why is that a determination for breaking into speech?
[SPEAKER_03]: Can you break into speech without having spoken?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, impossible.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, why is that?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's an irrelevant question.
[SPEAKER_03]: There is no... oh, well, this is how that happens.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is inseparable is that there is no breath apart from the body.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just... that is the base saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is inseparable is there is no breaking into speech without verbalized thinking.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is just the necessary basis for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, consequently, for the third saṅkhara, the mind and perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's inseparable from it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the reason why I'm saying this is because speech in particular, obviously, it's quite relevant for when comes people to practice meditation and so on, whatever their meditation means for them.
[SPEAKER_03]: But the point is, no matter how differently you're going about it, pretty much what is common is that everybody overlooks it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Everybody just wants to shut down the thoughts and the mental speaking, confusing it for this is a speech, this is a chatter.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, actually it isn't.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's unrestrained thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, that's for sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: But one thing is to restrain it, harness it, hone it, and another thing is to try to get rid of it and get that peace of no thinking.
[SPEAKER_03]: So first, develop it rightly, see the distinction, the different extent, the necessary basis, and then you'll know how to count down the rest.
[SPEAKER_03]: And those are the actual reflections that even Bodhisattva was doing, what we mentioned in that sutta.
[SPEAKER_03]: He says, oh, he would have a, I don't know, a hindrance of lust arise or thoughts of cruelty.
[SPEAKER_03]: He wasn't trying to get rid of it or stop thinking it.
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: He would start telling to himself, internally, this is for my own harm.
[SPEAKER_03]: Is this for benefit of me or others?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: What has this resulted in the past, engaging with sensuality?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, resulted in increasing the the the kind of unpredictability of my own mind,
[SPEAKER_03]: The lack of composure, the bad choices out of non-perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: You can tell all those things, not mechanically, but in relation to an enduring pressure of lust.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same, you have pressure of ill-will.
[SPEAKER_03]: Sure, you have a choice to act.
[SPEAKER_03]: Let's not act for a second.
[SPEAKER_03]: Stop, sit down quietly and review it, as the Buddha would say, in your own mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: Wait, this state that I'm being pressured by now, how many times it happened so far?
[SPEAKER_03]: By the way, I'm speaking this so you can hear me, but you should do this in your own head.
[SPEAKER_03]: How many times I've done this?
[SPEAKER_03]: I don't know.
[SPEAKER_03]: Did it ever result in completely free me from anger?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or did it ever not make things worse?
[SPEAKER_03]: Or did it not ever make me remorseful after?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: So it's it's all it's always universal and wholesome.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_03]: You don't even need to answer now whether you should act or not.
[SPEAKER_03]: You would have already subsided that anger by maintaining the correct perspective in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now,
[SPEAKER_03]: Do that thoroughly, day in, day out.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whenever anything unwholesome comes, you review it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Ask yourself direct questions in regard to the recent experience, not mechanical questions.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or just go through the motions of these mantra, repeating mantra questions, to get that experience ahead, when I actually did gain the perspective rightly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh no, it's the right perspective, right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you go back to it,
[SPEAKER_03]: Each time things arise, you question them rightly, verbally, internally.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, yeah, the time will come when you realize, okay, there's nothing unwholesome pressuring me.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why don't I stop this questioning and reviewing and constant maintenance of these wholesome thoughts?
[SPEAKER_03]: Let me just be mindful of this non-speaking mouth and stop talking even verbally in my mind.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you would have sufficiently tamed your mind by then.
[SPEAKER_03]: And by then, you could even plan for the second jhāna, which is exactly what Bodhisattva did.
[SPEAKER_03]: But, by not seeing where the line is, you'll be trying to get rid of the thoughts, or ignoring the verbal thinking, thinking, oh, that's just... this is where the practice is, while the actual root of the context and perspective starts with
[SPEAKER_03]: Verbalizing what is right here present.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not mechanically, like they did in Mahāsī, but actually with a question that points at the perspective of understanding what's presently endured.
[SPEAKER_04]: And that's developing perspective, developing strength, that's developing samādhi.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the step that's kind of overlooked, because of which you won't be able to go very far.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why even in the suttas, when somebody wanted, like Maha Moggallāna wanted to understand the first jhāna, when the Buddha encouraged him, he was, he told, he said to himself, basically, first jhāna, first jhāna, what is first jhāna?
[SPEAKER_03]: And started describing the factors, not on the level of information, but on the level of attending what is there, and being simultaneously described.
[SPEAKER_03]: By thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: Without breaking into speech.
[SPEAKER_04]: But it all comes from this first chariot of not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, see, if you don't put that first, all what I'm saying is, you could even get a glimpse of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, I can maintain the perspective.
[SPEAKER_03]: And then, out of lack of the proper development, you're gonna re-infuse it with the same old attitude of wanting a shortcut.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, instead of then enduring what's present, questioning yourself rightly to reveal the motivation in the context, you'll be just mechanically verbalizing, as I said, mantras, or like, oh, I'm sitting, I'm sitting, I'm touching, I'm feeling, I'm feeling, I'm perceiving, I'm perceiving, completely ignoring your intention behind it.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, yeah, verbalize whatever you want, and then verbalize the question, why are you verbalizing that in the first place?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why is this relevant to me?
[SPEAKER_03]: Why am I trying to verbalize these things so desperately?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, because I don't want to suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: All right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, suffering is back here.
[SPEAKER_03]: And how am I dealing with it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, by verbalizing random methods that I made mechanical, because I'm lacking proper development of sense restraint, gradual training.
[SPEAKER_03]: I have not endured things rightly on the right level sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, I just can't help it.
[SPEAKER_03]: I just need a fix, a shortcut.
[SPEAKER_03]: So then exactly, even if the Buddha himself is just telling you exactly what to do, you will make that into a method of an impersonal kind.
[SPEAKER_05]: So just once again, what is the physical activator, the verbal activator and the mental, the citta activator?
[SPEAKER_05]: Breathing is the physical saṃkhāra.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thinking and pondering is the verbal saṃkhāra.
[SPEAKER_05]: Perception and feeling are the mental saṃkhāra.
[SPEAKER_05]: How is breathing a physical saṃkhāra?
[SPEAKER_05]: How is thinking and pondering a verbal saṃkhāra?
[SPEAKER_05]: How is perception and feeling a mental saṃkhāra?
[SPEAKER_05]: Breathing is physical.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's tied up with the body.
[SPEAKER_05]: That is why breathing is a physical saṃkhāra.
[SPEAKER_05]: Having thought and pondered, reflected, you break into speech.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's why thought and reflection are verbal saṃkhāra.
[SPEAKER_05]: Perception and feeling are mental.
[SPEAKER_05]: They are tied up with the mind.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's why perception and feeling are mental processes, eh, activators.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how does someone attain the ending of perception and feeling?
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, the complete cessation of saṃkhāras.
[SPEAKER_05]: The complete cessation of saṃkhāras.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's the most refined one.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if you can attain that, it means you would have abandoned the speech and the breathing, for that matter.
[SPEAKER_03]: So... Well, by doing everything else we said, up to this point.
[SPEAKER_00]: I find the answer to this one quite good in relation to many other things as well.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: She says, a monk who is entering such an attainment does not think, I will enter the cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: Why?
[SPEAKER_01]: I am entering the cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: I've entered the cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: Rather, their mind has been previously developed so as to lead to such a state.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's the result of developing the same principle way before that.
[SPEAKER_05]: But there's there's no I am.
[SPEAKER_03]: There's no room even for such a thought, yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: No, because that's a perception.
[SPEAKER_05]: Oh, this must be perception, the cessation of perception feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, yes, which sees first for a monk who has, who is entering the cessation of perception feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: Physical, verbal or mental activators?
[SPEAKER_03]: Which one?
[SPEAKER_03]: Verbal.
[SPEAKER_03]: Verbal ceases first.
[SPEAKER_05]: Verbal ceases first, then the physical, then the mental.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, then the breathing.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: It would cease before the mental.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, how does someone emerge from cessation of perception and feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: A monk who is emerging from such an attainment does not think, I will emerge, I am emerging, or I have emerged from cessation of perception and feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: Rather, their mind has been previously developed so as to lead to such a state.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, which arise first for a monk who is emerging from the cessation of perception and feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: Physical, verbal or mental?
[SPEAKER_05]: And it's just the opposite, basically.
[SPEAKER_05]: Mental arise first, then the physical, then the verbal.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, when a monk has emerged from the attainment of this cessation of perception and feeling, how many kinds of pressure or contexts do they experience?
[SPEAKER_05]: They experience three kinds of pressures or contexts.
[SPEAKER_05]: Emptiness, sunyata, signlessness, nimitta, and undirected desire, apanīto.
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like... Non-specific.
[SPEAKER_05]: Non-specific desire, non-specific intention.
[SPEAKER_05]: I can't even understand it.
[SPEAKER_05]: I can't visualize it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, it goes hand-in-hand with signlessness.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sign is the specificity.
[SPEAKER_03]: See, the mind is established upon non-
[SPEAKER_03]: Non-specificity of signs, then, the only thing that can accompany is equally non-specific direction, which you wouldn't even call a desire, from the point of view of desires, that are always bound with the specific.
[SPEAKER_03]: And the emptiness, exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not the emptiness.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the empty of ownership, the empty of self, hollow of lust, aversion, hollow of that burning core that was existing before.
[SPEAKER_05]: But it's still a contact.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, again, sure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Technically, you can call it a contact, but only by abandoning the contact that non-Arahant has, you can understand the contact of an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because that's pretty much an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's an Arahant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Maybe the same as you left, I suppose, but...
[SPEAKER_05]: So, when a monk has emerged from the attainment of a cessation of perception and feeling, what does their mind incline to?
[SPEAKER_04]: Solitude.
[SPEAKER_04]: Seclusion.
[SPEAKER_05]: Their mind inclines to... Dispassion.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Detachment.
[SPEAKER_05]: How many feelings are there?
[SPEAKER_05]: There are three feelings.
[SPEAKER_05]: Pleasant, painful and neutral.
[SPEAKER_05]: What are these three feelings?
[SPEAKER_05]: Anything felt physical or mental as pleasant and enjoyable.
[SPEAKER_05]: Anything felt physical or mentally as painful or unpleasant, this is painful.
[SPEAKER_05]: Anything felt physically or mentally as neither pleasurable nor painful, this is neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is pleasant and what is painful in each of these feelings?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, pleasant feeling is pleasant when it remains and painful in its ending.
[SPEAKER_05]: Painful feeling is painful when it remains and pleasant in its ending.
[SPEAKER_05]: Neutral feeling is pleasant when known and unpleasant when not known.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, we spoke about it often.
[SPEAKER_05]: We just spoke about it the last time, didn't we?
[SPEAKER_03]: Probably.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what underlying tendencies underlie each of these three feelings?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, the underlying tendency for lust underlies pleasant feeling, the underlying tendency for resistance underlies painful feeling, the underlying tendency for ignorance underlies neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: Do these underlying tendencies always underlie these feelings?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, they do not.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what should be given up in regard to each of these three feelings?
[SPEAKER_05]: The underlying tendency to lust should be given up when it comes to pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: The underlying tendency to resistance should be given up when it comes to painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: The underlying tendency to ignorance should be given up when it comes to neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, so then... but it's obviously not as... practically speaking, because what is pleasant
[SPEAKER_03]: In a pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: And what is unpleasant in a pleasant feeling?
[SPEAKER_03]: You've just read that.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: When it's... Change.
[SPEAKER_03]: Changes.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you are then underline... underlied tendency for aversion towards the unpleasant aspect of the pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when there is a threat of change to something that's held dear and pleasant, you're averse to that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Although it's still that same pleasant experience, now it's the aversion underlying it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Or lust, when you equally carelessly accept it, take it for granted, want more of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's, again, none of that would be obvious, none of that would become apparent if somebody is first and foremost not acting out of their feelings, including feeling justified in trying to get rid of this lustful thought, that is obviously still regarded as pleasure, but now, because of all the other views, oh, that is, I must get rid of this, I must get rid of this, but now you're just fueling further that aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, either way, underlying tendencies remain and are being perpetuated.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you start with the pleasant feeling that's underlined by lust.
[SPEAKER_03]: Then, so, but lust is a problem, I must be restrained.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, you're averse to it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, again...
[SPEAKER_03]: Aversion is a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now, aversion is a problem.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, how do you fuel lust?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you fuel aversion?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you stop feeling lust?
[SPEAKER_03]: How do you stop feeling the aversion?
[SPEAKER_04]: Acting out of it or not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, obviously, when you're talking about the unpleasant aspect of a pleasant feeling, that is underlined, underlied by the aversion, that will be a subtle form, subtler form of action, but it's still an action.
[SPEAKER_03]: Aversive thoughts, aversive methods, rooted in aversion, trying to get rid of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's just your aversion.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's why you will remain bound to that which you're still lustful for.
[SPEAKER_03]: But if you don't feel the lust, nor you act out of aversion, you get to actually see it for what it is.
[SPEAKER_03]: But it's unpleasant now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you can't, well, abandon the underlying tendency of either lust or aversion by
[SPEAKER_03]: The only way you can abandon it is through attending to it concurrently, as we said.
[SPEAKER_03]: Concurrently attending to what is there a necessary basis for either your lust, or your aversion, or your actions that come out of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Oh, it's a feeling arisen on its own, still endures, agreeable, but now I perceive a danger in any form of engagement with it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Whether I reach for it to bring it closer, or whether I reach for it to push it away,
[SPEAKER_03]: Reaching for it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why I suffer.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's why I get burned.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not because the thing is there on its own.
[SPEAKER_03]: But that will not become apparent if you haven't attended to it rightly.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yoniso manasikāra.
[SPEAKER_03]: If you haven't attended to it concurrently, presence of that feeling means all these permutations and aversion and lust and acting and restraining, because this thing is there.
[SPEAKER_03]: And you get to see through all these movements and kind of
[SPEAKER_03]: Options and jumps of the mind, you actually perceive right through it what's at the other end of it, which is an enduring feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yoniso, this whole activity that I'm being overwhelmed and restraining and acting and justifying... Oh, presence and feeling, right.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, when that feeling is not present, all this is redundant.
[SPEAKER_03]: Okay, well, it's already redundant by seeing that.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's how you calm down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and in the same way, you cannot free yourself from the pressure of thinking and pondering by breaking into speech, because it's a completely separate domain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: And not just that.
[SPEAKER_03]: Like, when you do break into speech, you realize, as I said, the body is speaking for you.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are not doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's actually analogous to wanting to get rid of the pressure of sensuality by acting out bodily.
[SPEAKER_01]: In exactly the same way, you cannot free yourself from the pressure of thinking and pondering by breaking into speech, which is why both those domains need to be understood in order to dwell free from sensuality and unwholesome states.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the pressure, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the first jhāna.
[SPEAKER_03]: You are pressured by the domain you assumed can pressure you.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, you gave it power to pressure you and it's actually pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_03]: Obviously, there was no first point manifested before which you didn't give it power, and then you gave it power.
[SPEAKER_03]: You already find yourself overpowered by it, due to your own wrong notions and assumptions.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, should these underlying... should those underlying tendencies be given up regarding all instances of these feelings?
[SPEAKER_05]: So, it is... are there always these underlying tendencies to every single pleasant feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: No, there's no... not in all instances.
[SPEAKER_05]: Take a monk who is withdrawn from sensual desires, from sensual pleasures, desires for sensual pleasures, withdrawn from unskillful qualities, enters upon the first jhāna, which has the pleasure and joy born of withdrawal.
[SPEAKER_05]: Thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_05]: Well, thinking and pondering.
[SPEAKER_03]: With this, they give up lust and the underlying tendency to lust.
[SPEAKER_03]: Just to, again, specify in light of what we've just been saying.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, with quite a degree of activity of thinking and pondering,
[SPEAKER_03]: It's not thinking and pondering, but actually without thinking and pondering, which is what contemporary notions of jhānas would generally seem to imply.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yes, yes, thinking and pondering, but then when you look at it, oh, it's no thinking, no pondering, because that's too active.
[SPEAKER_03]: But no, no, with thinking and pondering, with verbal saṅkhara.
[SPEAKER_03]: Pleasure and joy, born of seclusion, born of safety.
[SPEAKER_03]: Safety from fully discerning the extent of the domains that cannot touch you, because you're not in them.
[SPEAKER_03]: Why would you worry about what's happening in the prison, when you realize you're not in it anymore?
[SPEAKER_03]: And you were in it before, because your assumption was keeping you in it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, that pleasure that is there...
[SPEAKER_03]: It's the pleasure of safety.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: Can you lust after this?
[SPEAKER_03]: Possible.
[SPEAKER_05]: Because it's the abandonment of that lust.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Do you need to get rid of it?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_03]: Would you fear if it changes?
[SPEAKER_03]: No, because you know that the change will have to be within the separate domains that you're safe from now.
[SPEAKER_03]: Thus, there will be no aversion towards it either.
[SPEAKER_05]: No fear of that change.
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: No fear, no aversion.
[SPEAKER_05]: And then, so, what about a painful feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is there an underlying tendency to aversion towards all painful feelings?
[SPEAKER_03]: No.
[SPEAKER_05]: It says, take a monk who thinks, oh, when will I enter and remain in that same dimension that the noble ones enter and remain in?
[SPEAKER_05]: And nursing such a longing for the supreme liberations gives rise to sadness.
[SPEAKER_05]: With this, they give up the resistance and underlying tendency to resistance does not lie underneath that.
[SPEAKER_03]: I mean, they give up the aversion.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah, they give up that resistance, they give up.
[SPEAKER_05]: Conversion towards that painful feeling of sadness.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's a pretty much painful feeling they were standing for.
[SPEAKER_03]: The domain that the noble ones dwell in.
[SPEAKER_03]: You just needed to stop resisting it.
[SPEAKER_03]: And when he finally stops resisting it, he's in the domain of the noble ones that are dwelling peacefully.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because now he's not averse towards it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, and then, in terms of neutral feeling, is that underlying tendency towards ignorance, does it underlie all neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: It says, no, take a monk who, abandoning pleasure and pain, and ending former happiness and sadness, enters upon the fourth jhāna, without pleasure or pain, with pure equanimity and recollection.
[SPEAKER_05]: With this, they give up ignorance, and the underlying tendency to ignorance does not lie.
[SPEAKER_03]: Under that.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, these are the last questions.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the counterpart of pleasant feeling?
Painful.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is it?
[SPEAKER_03]: Painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the Pali word for counterpart?
[SPEAKER_05]: It is counterpart.
[SPEAKER_05]: That's it.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, I don't quite understand the...
[SPEAKER_05]: It's like, what is the counterpart of pleasant feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the opposite?
[SPEAKER_05]: That's what he's asking.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the answer to the feelings.
[SPEAKER_05]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, painful feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the counterpart of painful feeling?
[SPEAKER_00]: Pleasant feeling.
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the counterpart of neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_03]: What's the counterpart of neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the opposite of neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_05]: Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_05]: I don't know how that's the answer.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the counterpart of neutral feeling?
[SPEAKER_03]: Ignorance.
[SPEAKER_03]: Presence of pain, of pleasant feeling counterpart would be pain, when that pleasure changes.
[SPEAKER_03]: The presence of painful feeling counterpart is pleasant, because it will have to disappear, the pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, then, you experience pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: The presence is outward.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like the other...
[SPEAKER_00]: The other end of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I was going to say.
[SPEAKER_00]: The other side.
[SPEAKER_03]: The other side of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: The other...
[SPEAKER_03]: So, presence of neutral feeling, it's ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: No knowledge.
[SPEAKER_05]: The other side of neutral feeling is ignorance.
[SPEAKER_05]: I still don't get that.
[SPEAKER_02]: Simultaneous.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, because you don't start neutral.
[SPEAKER_03]: When an enlightened mind experiences neutral feeling, it's being not understood.
[SPEAKER_03]: That is the presence there, of that neutral feeling.
[SPEAKER_03]: The counterpart of it.
[SPEAKER_03]: Not after.
[SPEAKER_03]: At the same time.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is the counterpart of ignorance?
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, non-ignorance.
[SPEAKER_03]: So now, when ignorance is seen as present, well, see, you stopped ignoring it.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's the other side.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's another simultaneous thing now.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's why you couldn't... you could only answer that question, like, what is the counterpart or the other end of neutral feeling, if you had already kind of understood the counterpart of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Otherwise, that's just all invisible, basically.
[SPEAKER_05]: To some extent, and then...
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, you could start, sort of, carving it from the inside, but it will take a while.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is the counterpart of ignorance?
[SPEAKER_05]: Is it non-ignorance or knowledge?
[SPEAKER_05]: What is the counterpart of knowledge?
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is... what is the present end of present knowledge?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the other present?
[SPEAKER_04]: I can't think of a better word, actually.
[SPEAKER_04]: It's like liberation and more... Dispassion?
[SPEAKER_05]: Liberation.
[SPEAKER_05]: Freedom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Freedom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Presence of knowledge means freedom is present, liberation is present, dispassion is present.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, if the knowledge is present sufficiently long, its counterpart will be equally present sufficiently long enough for you to fully then see liberation, freedom as that which is present now.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, what is the counterpart of that?
[SPEAKER_05]: Of freedom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_03]: Well, that's complete nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_05]: Nibbāna.
[SPEAKER_05]: So, what is the counterpart of nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_03]: What is the counterpart of that nibbāna?
[SPEAKER_03]: That designation does not reach that.
[SPEAKER_05]: And the nun, she answers Visakha, your question goes too far.
[SPEAKER_01]: You couldn't figure out the limits of questions.
[SPEAKER_05]: For nibbāna is the culmination, the destination, and the goal is holy life.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, also nibbāna is the undetermined, so how can it have an opposite?
[SPEAKER_03]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, that is the end of it.
[SPEAKER_04]: This... that... the counterpart of knowledge being freedom, to me, also points to this... this... the fact that... the suffering is the ultimate... coming out of suffering is like the ultimate...
[SPEAKER_04]: So, what is the ultimate knowledge?
[SPEAKER_04]: What is the ultimate counterpart?
[SPEAKER_04]: It's freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_04]: Intention that anyone can have that isn't rooted in wanting to come out of suffering, wanting freedom.
[SPEAKER_03]: Yeah, I think, basically, as long as, as long as the... just to highlight, to repeat, the counterpart, its simultaneous presence, it should not be understood as of what comes later.
[SPEAKER_03]: So, it's like, as I said, painful feeling is implied in current pleasure.
[SPEAKER_03]: Because, current pleasure we have to change, and there will have to be, then, felt painfully.
[SPEAKER_03]: And that's already painful.
[SPEAKER_03]: Knowledge, that just presence of that pleasure to an ignorant mind, it already implies pain.
[SPEAKER_03]: Same.
[SPEAKER_03]: Presence of pain already implies pleasure, because it will have to end one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_03]: Neutral feeling implies ignoring.
[SPEAKER_03]: Now you see ignoring, well, that implies non-ignoring.
[SPEAKER_05]: Not ignoring.
[SPEAKER_05]: You see distraction.
[SPEAKER_04]: Yeah, you could say that.
[SPEAKER_04]: And like the eightfold path, this isn't linear?
[SPEAKER_04]: No, no.
[SPEAKER_03]: It's as you said, it's the three aspects of one development, which is development of dispassion and freedom from suffering.
[SPEAKER_03]: That's it.